Harwich, Mass. First Congregational Church records, 1726-1982.
Congregational Library & Archives
Harwich, Mass. First Congregational Church records, 1726-1982.
RG0089
Congregational Library & Archives
2.53 Cubic Feet
(3 boxes, 2 reels)
The First Congregational Church of Harwich, Massachusetts, was founded in 1747 when the town of Harwich was split into the North and South Parishes. On April 8, 1747, the precinct voted to complete construction on a meeting house which was finally completed in 1748. In 1792, the second meetinghouse was completed after the first had been condemned a year earlier. The church officially became known as the First Congregational Church of Harwich when the church became incorporated in 1898 at the behest of the Rev. George Y. Washburn. The First Church of Harwich continues to serve the community today. The collection documents the history, administration, and life of the church and includs membership lists, church and parish records, and administrative/legal documents.
Church of Christ (Harwich, Mass.)
First Congregational Church (Harwich, Mass.)
Washburn, Geroge Y.
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Materials deposited to the Congregational Library & Archives by the First Congregational Church of Harwich in 1981; no accession number.
The Draft deed was donated to the Congregational Library & Archives by the First Congregational Church of Harwich in 2022, 2022-18.
Digital Copies
Records within this collection were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories project. Digital reproductions may be accessed online through our digital archive.
Historical Note
Prior to the arrival of European colonists, the lands that encompass today's Harwich were inhabited by the Wampanoag. Harwich was first settled by Europeans in 1670 as part of Yarmouth. Harwich was separately incorporated in 1694.
The First Congregational Church of Harwich, Massachusetts, was founded in 1747 when the town of Harwich was split into the North and South Parishes. Efforts to split the town in half had begun in 1744 when families from the south side of Harwich petitioned the town meeting to separate the southern portion into its own distinct precinct. This and several other attempts were denied until a petition to the Massachusetts General Court resulted in the eventual separation of Harwich into two "distinct and separate precinct[s]" effective January 16, 1747. On April 8, 1747, the precinct voted to begin construction of a meeting house with construction being completed the following year. Also, in April of 1747, Edward Pell, a Harvard graduate and Boston native, preached to the South Parish. Not long after, he was called by the South Parish to become the first pastor of the South Parish, a call he accepted graciously. Pell was ordained to the office on November 12, 1747. As part of his salary, Pell was given a "convenient hovel." This structure was finally completed in 1751. Pell perished in 1752 and his widow left to Maine in 1753. At this time, their home became the parsonage and "Ministerial House" for future pastors. It did not remain as such for long as in 1782 the house and barn were sold to cover precinct expenses. The period between 1773 and 1792 was particularly rocky for the church, marked by numerous religious dissensions, shared pulpits with the West Harwich Baptist Church, and general unrest which resulted in the quick succession of multiple pastors during this period.
In 1792, the second meetinghouse was completed after the first had been condemned a year earlier. With the new meetinghouse came a new minister, Nathan Underwood, whose name became synonymous with the second meetinghouse. Underwood served the parish for thirty-six years, the longest ministry at the church. During his time at the First Congregational Church, Underwood expanded the membership of the church, advocated for further independence for the South Precinct, and taught numerous others "scientific" farming. He retired from active service in 1819, though he continued to offer support until 1828 when his relation with the church was formally dissolved. Shortly before his death, Underwood sold his home to the town for use as an almshouse. By 1832 the second meetinghouse needed to be replaced, and by the fall of that year Moses B. Lakeman completed construction. Financial difficulties and short pastorates marked the church's history until 1851 when the Rev. Moses Hale Wilder began a complete reorganization of the church's administration. He also oversaw the first expansion of the third meetinghouse in 1854.
The church officially became known as the First Congregational Church of Harwich when the church became incorporated under Massachusetts state law on December 19, 1898 at the behest of the Rev. George Y. Washburn. Washburn, further, celebrated the 150th anniversary of the church by writing a history of the congregation in 1897.
The first third of the 20th century was again marked by financial and parishioner distress with few pastors remaining long and the congregation growing smaller. That changed in 1933 with George Hunt who helped to revitalize the church community. His wife, Ruth Hunt, became the first woman to preach at the First Church after her husband fell ill one weekend. After World War II, Harwich, along with the rest of the Massachusetts cape, had become something of a tourist resort town. The result has been a revitalized church which has become welcoming to locals and visitors alike. The 200th anniversary of the church saw a complete renovation of the third meetinghouse. In 1954, a chapel first built by the Ladies of the Sewing Circle in 1881 was repurposed into the Parish House. In 1961, the church voted to become a member of the United Church of Christ. The First Church of Harwich continues to serve the community today.
Ministers
Edward Pell 1746-1752
Benjamin Crocker 1754-1756
John Dennis 1756-1761
Benjamin Crocker 1761-1765
Jonathan Mills 1766-1773
No regular minister 1774-1776
Joseph Litchfield 1777-1778
Samuel Nickerson 1778-1787
Jonathan Jeffers 1787-1789
Asa Hunt 1790-1791
Nathan Underwood 1792-1828
Isaac W. Wheelwright 1826-1827
William M. Cornell 1828-1829
Lucius Field 1830
Powers 1831
Caleb Kimball 1832-1834
William Withington 1835
Charles S. Adams 1835-1838
John H. Avery 1838-1839
William Marchant 1840-1841
James D. Farnsworth 1841
William H. Adams 1841-1844
Cyrus Stone 1844-1848
Theophilus F. Sawin 1848-1851
Moses Hale Wilder 1851-1858
Joseph Rice Munsell 1858-1868
William H. Beard 1869-1870
Charles S. Whitney 1871-1872
Bradish G. Ward 1872-1876
Joseph Hammond 1876-1877
Smith Norton 1878-1879
S.W. Powell 1880
Rufus B. Tobey 1880-1883
Cassius M. Westlake 1884-1885
Henry P. Cutting 1885-1888
F.J. Ward 1890
John C. Staples 1891-1892
J. Walter Sylvester 1893
J.H. Whittaker, Jr. 1893-1894
Artemas J. Haynes 1894-1896
George Y. Washburn 1896-1899
Charles H. Rowley 1899-1904
Henry A. Ryder 1905-1910
Frederick T. Knight 1910-1912
George W. Clark 1913-1918
Jack Hyde 1919-1920
F.B. Noyes 1920-1922
F.W. Hoisington 1923-1924
B.D.F. Lindsay 1924-1928
Howard R. May 1928-1929
Walter M. Stone 1930-1931
Leon S. Kelley 1931-1932
George A. Hunt 1933-1936
Henry D. Newell 1936-1943
George Loring Thurlow 1943-1953
Harry L. Meyer 1953-1959
J. Edward Elliot 1960-1971
Albert C. Ronander 1971-1978
H.L. Meyer 1976-1982
J.R. Williams 1981-1984
M.B. Carver-Schad 1981-2007
C.T. Newberry 1985-2006
L.C. Toppan 1986-1995
E. Deasy 1988-1989
J.N. Erickson 1990-1997
J.C. Pearsall 1997-1998
A. Weirch 1998-2001
T.C. Leinbach 2006-2017
Susan E. Thomas 2021-present
Scope and Contents
The Harwich, Mass. First Congregational Church records document the history, administration, and life of the church, including membership lists, church and parish records, meeting minutes, financial documents, society records, legal documents, church publications, committee reports, subscription lists, a manuscript by George Y. Washburn, and microfilmed copies of original records.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into the five series listed below. The records are arranged primarily by chronological order and then topic.
Series 1: Church and Society Records, 1745-1974
Series 2: Administrative Records, 1726-1982
Series 3: Church Subscriptions, 1832-1857
Series 4: Rev. George Y. Washburn Manuscript, circa 1897, 1972
Series 5: Microfilm, 1981
Technical Requirements
To access digital user's copies via online-interface, a java-enabled web browser is required. Internet Explorer 8.x and later, Firefox 5.x and later, Opera 12 and later, Safari 5.x and later, or any version of Google Chrome are recommended.
A microfilm reader is required in order to access microform materials. One microfilm reader is available to the public upon request.
Bibliography
History: First Congregational Church Harwich, Massachussetts 1747-1972. Harwich: Jack Viall, 1972. 17.11.1 H26.67 FirCC
Baptismal records.; Church finance.; Church lands.; Church membership.; Church records and registers.; Creeds.; Marriage records.; New England's Hidden Histories.; Church of Christ (Harwich, Mass.); First Congregational Church (Harwich, Mass.); Harwich (Mass.) -- Church history.
- Church and Society records, 1745 1974; 1745-1974; 16 Volumes
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes the records or the church and parish as well as records of societies attached to the church. Included within the records are meeting minutes, baptismal records, marriage records, committee reports, financial documents, annual reports, and historical notes.
  - Parish records, 1746 1792; 1746-1792 (Box 1, Volume 1)
    Physical Access
    These records are unavailable for patron use due to fragility. Use the 19th century copy of these records. Contact the archivist for special permission to view the originals.
    Location of Copies
    These records were transcribed and edited by Obed Brooks and made the first part of the Records of the First Parish, 1745-1899.
  - Proprietors' records, 1791 1793; 1791-1793 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    The Proprietors' Records include meeting minutes, financial records, receipts, pew deeds, treasurer reports, and the church ledger for the years 1791-1793.
  - Church records volume 1, 1792 1835; 1792-1835 (Box 1, Volume 3)
    This record book contains church records dating from 1792-1835. Included within these records are the Church Covenant, church proceedings, lists of admitted members, lists of members received from other churches, lists of members removed to other churches, baptismal records, dates for the administration of the supper, and marriage records.
  - Church records volume 2, 1792 1857; 1792-1857 (Box 1, Volume 4)
    This record book contains parish records dating from 1792-1857. Included within these records are the minutes of church and parish meetings, minutes of government meetings, legal calls of assembly, and financial records.
  - Records of the First Parish, 1745 1899; 1745-1899; 1830 1899; 1830-1899 (Box 3)
    This record book contains the records of the First Parish from 1745-1899. The records dating from 1745-1803 are handwritten transcribed copies of the original oldest records of the church. They were transcribed by Obed Brooks who also edited and annotated the records. The Congregational Library & Archives holds an incomplete collection of those original documents which are now considered too fragile to handle. All records in the book from 1830-1899 were original. Included within these records are the minutes of church and parish meetings, minutes of precinct meetings, legal calls of assembly, church correspondence, the original members list, and treasurer accounts.
  - Minister's records, 1832 1855; 1832-1855 (Box 1, Volume 5)
    This record book contains parish records dating from 1832-1855. Included within these records are building dedications, the form of the first covenant, the Confession of Faith, the Church Covenant, the Confession of Faith and Covenant, records of church business, admissions lists, baptismal records, lists of dismissions, church by-laws, records pertaining to the organization of the church, marriage records, church meeting minutes, lists of deaths and funerals, lists of subscribers, and membership lists.
  - Church and Parish meetings, 1855 1899; 1855-1899 (Box 1, Volume 6)
  - Young Peoples' Society records, 1887 1895; 1887-1895 (Box 1, Volume 7)
  - Records of the First Congregational Church of Harwich, 1900 1940; 1900-1940 (Box 1, Volume 8)
  - Records of the First Congregational Church of Harwich, 1941 1954; 1941-1954 (Box 1, Volume 9)
  - Records of the First Congregational Church of Harwich, 1956 1960; 1956-1960 (Box 1, Volume 10)
  - Records of the First Congregational Church of Harwich, 1961 1962; 1961-1962 (Box 1, Volume 11)
  - Records of the First Congregational Church of Harwich, 1963 1964; 1963-1964 (Box 2, Volume 1)
  - Records of the First Congregational Church of Harwich, 1965 1966; 1965-1966 (Box 2, Volume 2)
  - Records of the First Congregational Church of Harwich, 1966 1971; 1966-1971 (Box 2, Volume 3)
  - Records of the First Congregational Church of Harwich, 1971 1974; 1971-1974 (Box 2, Volume 4)
- Administrative records, 1726 1982; 1726-1982; 15 Files; (5 volumes, 10 folders)
  This series includes records related to the administration and functions of the First Congregational Church. Included in the records are legal documents such as land deeds and calls of assembly, correspondence, reports of the treasurer and committees, and church publications.
  - Deed of land, 1726 1727; 1726-1727 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Church register, 1746 1747; 1746-1747; 2 Items (Box 2, Folder 2)
    This folder includes two documents which cover the founding of the First Congregational Church of Harwich in the newly established South Parish. Included in the documents is a list of the founding members of the church and a copy of the petition to the Massachusetts General Court which resulted in the formation of the South Parish.
  - Draft deed, 1747 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Sale of land, 1748 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Calls to assembly, 1789 1796; 1789-1796 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Church communications, 1792 1828; 1792-1828; 4 Items (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Digital Copies
    These church records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories project. Digital reproductions are available to view online.
    Included in this folder are four documents which generally represent communications and correspondence from the church. Included is a receipt, a letter by Rev. Nathan Underwood, a call to vote for church officers, and a communication to Rev. Underwood regarding his official end of pastoral duties.
  - Articles of Faith and Covenant, 1832 (Box 2, Volume 5)
  - Treasurer's report, 1832 1838; 1832-1838 (Box 2, Volume 6)
    This volume contains 30 pages of financial records dating from 1832-1855. Included within these records are the church ledger, receipts, pew numbers and prices, and lists of contributions collected.
  - Harwich Sunday School class book, 1836 (Box 2, Volume 7)
  - Church correspondence, 1838 1876; 1838-1876 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Town disturbance, 1863 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Discipline of Obed Brooks, 1874 1875; 1874-1875 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Manual of the Congregational Church, 1881 (Box 2, Volume 8)
  - Church By-laws, 1898 (Box 2, Volume 9)
  - Committee notes and reports, 1941 1965; 1941-1965 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Church publications, 1981 1982; 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Church Subscriptions, 1832 1857; 1832-1857; 5 Files; (4 volumes, 1 folder)
  This series includes records related to church subscriptions as part of fundraising for building projects. Included in the records are subscriptions lists and receipts.
  - Subscription receipts, 1832 1835; 1832-1835 (Box 2, Volume 10)
    This volume contains 55 pages of records dating from 1832-1835. Included within these records are receipts which list the date issued, the holder of the receipt, and the date that the receipts were paid off. Also included is a list of members who had paid dues.
  - Subscription receipts, 1832 1838; 1832-1838 (Box 2, Volume 11)
    This volume contains 32 pages of records dating from 1832-1838. Included within these records are receipts which list the date issued, the holder of the receipt, and the date that the receipts were paid off. Also included are breif financial notes.
  - List of subscriptions, 1836 (Box 2, Volume 12)
    This volume contains 25 pages of records dated 1836. Included within these records are a list of members not paid, additional subscription receipts, subscriptions paid by labor, and financial calculations.
  - Subscription paper, 1854 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Subscriptions: Remodeling of the Church, 1855 1857; 1855-1857 (Box 2, Volume 13)
- Rev. George Y. Washburn Manuscript, 1897 1972; circa 1897, 1972; 6 Folders
  This series includes the a manuscript written by the Rev. George Y. Washburn on the occasion of the 150th anniversary of the First Congregational Church which covers the history of Harwich and the church. Also included in the materials are Washburn's collected notes and contemporary summaries of Washburn's work made in preparation for the 225th anniversary of the church.
  - Washburn manuscript, circa 1897 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Washburn summaries, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Washburn notes I, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Washburn notes II, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Washburn notes III, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Washburn notes IV, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Microfilm, 1981; 2 Reels
  Included in this series are two reels of microfilmed copies of church and parish records.
  Existence and Location of Originals
  Originals of microfilmed records can be found within this collection.
  - Records of the First Congregational Church of Harwich, 1981 (Box H2, Reel 1)
    Index
    Original Deed
    Records: 1745-1899
    Ministers Record: 1792
    Records: 1792-1855
    Ministers Records: 1832-1855
    Church & Parish Meetings: 1855-1899
    Records: 1940-1966
  - Records of the First Congregational Church of Harwich, 1981 (Box H2, Reel 2)
    Records: 1966-1975
    Washburn papers
    Benjamin Smalley and Sam Nickerson Petition to Gen. Court
    Articles of Faith: 1840
    Manual: 1887
    Subscriptions: 1832, 1855-1857
    Church by-laws: 1898
    Christian Endeavor